Guide to the Naval History Society Collection 1721-1995 (bulk 1781-1936) MS 439
New-York Historical Society
- Series 49. Logbooks: U.S. Navy (1799-1928, undated)
  The 1824 USS Ontario cruise was via the West Indies to the Mediterranean, where it joined Commodore William Bainbridge's (see Series 1) squadron and protected commercial shipping along the Barbary Coast from pirates. The volume includes drawings and writing at the end, probably by the child or children of Murray Mason, Fairfax County, Virginia. A midshipman at the time of this log, he may have been on Ontario and returned home with the book.
  USS Potomac departed New York in August, 1831, on its first overseas cruise to join the Pacific Station via the Cape of Good Hope. On February 6, 1832, it shelled Quallah Batoo, Sumatra, in retaliation for the February, 1831, capture of merchant vessel Friendship and the murder of her crew. The logbook was kept by midshipman James L. Parker. In the volume are two newspaper clippings: "View of the Castle of San Juan d'Ulua with the burning of the Mexican brig Creole by Lieutenant James Lawrence Parker and passed midshipmen Hynson and Rodgers USN" (undated) and from "The Daily chronicle and General Advertiser" of August 7, 1847, a memoriam from Commodore Matthew C. Perry on Parker's July 12, 1847, death from disease brought on by wounds sustained in an attack on Tuspan, Mexico.
  The Constelation [sic] and Grampus logbooks are bound on continuous sheets that appear to have been removed from a previously sewn volume. The title page of each shows a hand-rendered drawing of the ship at full sail.
  The 1844 Constitution logbook documents a cruise to the African coast off Madagascar. It includes hand-drawn maps of the area showing the ship's route and one with soundings documented; appendices on "Madagascar," "Hints on the Economy of a Man of War" (noting health and cleanliness issues on a long cruise to an unhealthy place), "The comparative merits of hemp and chain cablesvaluable extract from a report transmitted by the Board of Admiralty by Captain W.F. Owen Royal Navy," "Chronological abstract of the cruise," "Barometrical observations in the Mozambique Channel during the months of October and November 1844," "Wooden Anchors," and "The Mozambique channel".
  The Penguin logbook documents routine shipboard operations during travel between Key West, Charlotte Harbor, and Apalachicola, Florida, before ending at Baltimore, Maryland, as part of the ship's protection of Union naval forces during the Civil War.
  The Serapis logbooks were edited by John Sanford Barnes (see Series 3, Series 28) and published as "The logs of the Serapis - Alliance - Ariel, under the command of John Paul Jones, 1779-1780; with extracts from public documents, unpublished letters and narratives," by the DeVinne Press, New York, as the Society's first volume of publications in 1911.
  - U.S.S. Ontario, 1837 October 19 - 1838 March 8 (Box OS 1, Folder 23)
  - Journal of a cruise on board of the USS; U.S. Schooner Grampus, 1838 March 16 - October 20; 1839 August 26 - 1840 July 31 (Box OS 1, Folder 24)
  - Logs of Serapis, Alliance, Ariel, under the Command of John Paul Jones, 1779-1780 (Volume 1)
  - USS Ontario, 1824 July 24 - 1825 July 23 (Volume 2)
  - Journal of Pacific Cruise US Frigate Potomac, 1831 August 23 - 1833 13 June, 1847 (Volume 3)
  - Log of U.S. Frigate Constitution, 1844 March 26 - October 31 (Volume 4)
  - Steam log of U.S. Steamer Penguin, 1862 July 22 - May 22 1863 (Volume 5)
  - Log of the U.S. Frigate Constitution, 1798 July 20 - May 11 [photostat], 1928 (Volume 6)
  - A log book for the ship Bon Homme Richard, the honorible [sic] John Paul Jones, Commander. Begun at L'Orient, Saturday 8th of May 1779 [transcript], Undated (Volume 7)
  - A log book for the war ship Ranger, John Paul Jones, Commander. 1777 November 26 - ends 1778 May 18 [transcript], Undated (Volume 8)
- Series 50. Logbooks: British Navy (1758-1933; bulk, 1807-1837)
  The series consists of 13 volumes of original and transcribed logbooks from British naval vessels. Except for the Duke of Cumberland, Defiance, and Patuxent River documents (Volumes 1, 2, 12), the logbooks appear to have been cut from previously sewn or bound volumes before being rehoused as unbound sheets in buckram boxes. Many are missing up to 1 inch of what would have been their left-hand margins and some include duplicate chronological sections.
  Duke of Cumberland was a privately owned New York vessel licensed to the British navy (a so-called privateer) to capture and confiscate French merchant ships during the 7 Years' War (1756-1763). The log documents two West Indian cruises including the capture of Dolphin, Eagle, and Grand Joseph in February, 1759.
  The Patuxent River logs are transcripts from the records of HMS Tonnant, HMS Loire, HMS Jaseur, HMS Severn, HMS St. Lawrence, HMS Royal Oak, HMS Hebrus, and HMS Dragon as they confronted American gunboats on the approach to Washington City between June and September of 1814.
  The HMS Barfleur and HMS London transcripts document involvement in the Battle of the Chesapeake, in which the former was the flagship of Samuel Hood and the latter of Hood's superior, Sir Thomas Graves. The battle was lost to the French under the command of Admiral de Grasse (see Series 18), which had a significant effect on the outcome of the American war.
  The remaining logs document routine cruises, including HMS Poictiers in British waters and the West Indies; Beagle while sailing for the Bay of Biscay to join the Duke of Wellington's forces against Napoleon; and Cressy off the north coast of Europe, in English waters, and the West Indies.
  - Log Book Duke of Cumberland, 1758 December 23 - 1760 July 17 (Volume 1)
  - A journal of the proceedings of H.M. Ship Defiance, Henry Hotham esquire captain, 1807 February -1809 February 10 (Volume 2)
  - A log and proceedings of His Majesty's ship Poictiers, 1808 March 9 - 1812 November 14 (Volume 3)
  - Log books HMS Pomone, 1808 July 1 - 1813 June 13 (Volume 4)
  - Log books His Majesty's sloop Carolina, 1808 July 7 - 1810 July 1 (Volume 5)
  - Log of the proceedings on board His Majesty's ship Powerful on her passage from Bombay towards the Cape of Good Hope, from thence to St. Helena and thence to England, Chas. Jas. Johnston Esq. Capt kept by George Tippet Lt., 1808 September 14 - 1809 September 13 (Volume 6)
  - Log books His Majesty's sloop Princess Carolina, 1810 January 26 - 1813 June 13 (Volume 7)
  - Log books His Majesty's sloop Beagle, 1811 February 14 - 1813 November 6 (Volume 8)
  - Log books His Majesty's ship Cressy, 1811 October 6 - 1814 May 26 (Volume 9)
  - Log books His Majesty's gun brig Leverett [copy], 1832 July 1 - 1833 December 31 (Volume 10)
  - Log books His Majesty's ship Dee, 1832 June 25 - 1837 April 6 (Volume 11)
  - Captains' logs of principal British ships in Patuxent River operations during advance on Washington, 1814 June 6 - September 3 [transcript], About 1933 (Volume 12)
  - Log books of His Majesty's ships Barfleur and London; extracts from 1781 August 29 - September 13 [transcript], Undated (Volume 13)
- Series 51. Logbooks: Commercial vessels (1799-1865, undated)
  The series consists of 20 volumes of logbooks from six sail or steam commercial vessels on routine cruises, and 15 cod-fishing vessels from York, Maine, on their annual journeys to the Bay of Fundy and St. Lawrence River fishing grounds.
  America's 1799-1800 logbook was probably kept by Michael Hayes (nephew of John Barry, and relative of John Sanford Barnes's wife; see Series 3, Series 5) on a voyage from Philadelphia to China via Lisbon.
  Mary also sailed the China route, from Philadelphia to Canton via Batavia under Christian Christianson, master, between May 14, 1832 and April 4, 1833. Camilla, under James T. Watkins, master, made port in Rio de Janeiro, Cowes (Isle of Wight), and Antwerp before ending its cruise in Tarragona, Spain, from October 6, 1834 to March 1, 1835. The volume concludes with various non-voyage-related writings: "The Marriage Vow" on wifely fidelity, as well as detailed descriptions of female anatomy and various gynecological disorders. It turns over to an "Inventory of my Effects" dated Philadelphia, 1832, which lists debts incurred and monies due, as well as merchandise, stocks, and money held; a penciled draft of a letter to a loved one; and several poems.
  SS Republic cruised from New York to San Francisco via Rio, and America in 1863 from New York to Panama.
  The Governor Clinton log was a gift of Caspar Goodrich's daughter, Mrs. C.T. Davis, on the same date with other materials now collected in Series 21. This typed, corrected transcript documents a voyage from Peru to New York on which Caspar Goodrich's grandfather James W. Goodrich sailed under Captain L.B. Griswold, who was accused of drunkenness and other misbehaviors.
  The fishing ships' logbooks are preprinted volumes that include regulations for the registration of vessels and their catches, and are filled in by hand to document the voyages, conditions, and amount of fish caught.
  Related Materials at New-York Historical Society
  Series 21, Subseries IV. James Griswold journal transcripts, includes additional information about James Griswold, from the Goodrich donation.
  - Log book ship America, 1799-1800 (Volume 1)
  - Log book ship Mary; brig Camilla, 1832 May 14 - 1835 March 1 (Volume 2)
  - SS Republic, 1850 April 13 - 1852 February 7 (Volume 3)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Wonder of York, 1853 May 30 - November 3 (Volume 4)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Wonder of York, 1854 June 1 - November 25 (Volume 5)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing schooner Elizabeth of York, 1856 April 30 - November 29 (Volume 6)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing schooner Rescue of York and Kittery, 1856 May 16 - November 7 (Volume 7)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing schooner Josephine of York, 1857 April 11 - November 2 (Volume 8)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Hannah of York, 1857 April 28 - October 19 (Volume 9)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Golden Cloud of York, 1857 June 1 - November 5 (Volume 10)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Julia Ann of York, 1858 May 16 - November 1 (Volume 11)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Eagle of York, 1858 June 2 - October 26 (Volume 12)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing schooner Josephine of York, 1859 April 19 - November 30 (Volume 13)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Eagle of York, 1859 May 5 - November 5 (Volume 14)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Golden Cloud of York, 1859 May 10 - November 29 (Volume 15)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Victoria of York, 1860 May 11 - October 25 (Volume 16)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing schooner Webster of York, 1863 March 17 - July 26 (Volume 17)
  - Steamship America, 1863 November 1 - December 31 (Volume 18)
  - Journal of a voyage, fishing boat Black Jacob of Gloucester, 1865 June 14 - November 10 (Volume 19)
  - "Journal of Remarkable Transactions & Occurances [sic] on Board of the Ship Governor Clinton Homeward Bound from Payta "coast of Peru" to New York in 1828", 1828 July 3 - October 6 [transcript], Undated (Volume 20)
- Series 52. Miscellaneous manuscripts
  The series consists of more than 1100 letters, clippings, reprints, and other documents amassed by John Sanford Barnes and others to, from, and about notable persons including many with named series in this collection (e.g., William Bainbridge [Series 1], John Barry [Series 5], French E. Chadwick [Series 8], Gustavus Conyngham [Series 10], Gustavus Vasa Fox [Series 17], Caspar F. Goodrich [Series 21], Isaac Hull [Series 27], John Paul Jones [Series 28], Richard Worsam Meade 3rd [Series 31], Oliver Hazard Perry [Series 36], Henry A. Wise [Series 48]).
  The organization of the materials into this series is somewhat arbitrary. In some cases a document was removed from a named collection and specifically located here (see Henry A. Wise letter removed from letter book). In other cases there was not sufficient material on a particular person to warrant creation of a series. Individual signatures have, in some instances, been cut from their original document for inclusion here, and a name does not necessarily signify an autograph document: the Jefferson material consists of a letter addressed to him. Some folders function more as subject files than manuscript collections: they may include information collected about a person rather than correspondence to or from them.
  Some of the letters are addressed to Captain Barnes; others show evidence of having been purchased by him or donated to the Naval History Society. Many are addressed to Captain Garrett J. Pendergrast, commander of the Philadelphia Navy Yard. No explanation is given for their inclusion here in such profusion. Some documents have been mounted for display and/or sale; on a few the purchase price is marked in pencil.
  This series functions in parallel and complementary to the previous 51 series in the collection. Together with Barnes's List of officers' autograph letters signed (Series 44) and his documentation of extra-illustrations for Cooper's "History of the Navy of the United States" (Series 11), it further documents his, and the Society's, collection and organization of autograph materials.
  The extensive Bainbridge materials in this series provide additional evidence of the Barnes family's interest in, and collecting activities related to, their illustrious forebear. Information organized here on the location and history of documents complements that in Dearborn's extra-illustrated life of Bainbridge (Series 1). The John Paul Jones material (foldered here under John Sanford Barnes) could as well have been part of Series 28, since it includes additional correspondence of Barnes with Jones's biographer Anna deKoven, and about Robert Dale and the donation of a sword purportedly owned by him and now in the collection of New-York Historical Society.
  Highlights of the series include documents signed by Presidents John Quincy Adams (Bainbridge folder 5, Barry folder 1) and James Madison; others signed by John C. Calhoun, Salmon P. Chase, Richard Henry Dana, David Farragut, Robert Fulton, John Hancock, Rufus King, Seth Low, Robert Morris, and Matthew C. Perry; and a lock of Abraham Lincoln's hair removed after his death and sent by Robert Todd Lincoln to Gustavus Vasa Fox (removed from Series 17; now in Series 52, Box 5) at the latter's request.
  Caspar Goodrich's 1907 letter of thanks for Barnes' sympathies at the death of Goodrich's son includes mention of the young man's portrait as a boy painted by John Singer Sargeant. Among David Porter's letters are cartoons and drawings by him, including one of animal-headed naval officers listening to explanations of the value of steam-powered vessels, which complement others in the Fox collection (Series 17). The William Smith folder includes a map of an attack on Whampoa, China, in 1870. It is unclear what Barnes's connection was to Nikola Tesla: letters from him indicate that he had visited Barnes in New York in 1904. The William C. Whitney document appears to be a personal financial report related to stock holdings but has been retained here.
  Miscellaneous manuscripts collections are artificial gatherings of single or small groups of letters, often including individual letters signed by notable persons. As such, they can be troves of autograph or highpoint materials, a specialty of later 19th and early 20th century correspondence collectors. They document that era of collecting tastes and do not reflect modern archival precepts of original order or the maintenance of a document's physical or historical context or provenance.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by the subject's name, with Miscellaneous collections placed at the end of a letter's run. It includes an index organized by 200 "portfolio" numbers, probably referring to the collection's original alphabetical order. This provides detailed descriptions of individual documents, which can be matched to the current alphabetical arrangement.
  John Sanford Barnes detailed his collecting interests and activities in a lecture he delivered at the Naval War College in 1902, which was published as "Naval Literature" by Captain John S. Barnes in Proceedings of the United States Naval Institute, volume XXIX, no. 2, whole no. 106, p. 32 (XN E182 .B26).
  - Index, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Henry A.: Letters, 1860, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, John Quincy: Midshipman's warrant, ship's passport, 1825, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agassiz, Jean Louis Rodolphe: Letter, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Almy, John J.: Letters, 1834 [?] - 1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amory, E. Linzee: Letter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Armstrong, William M.: Letters, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aspinwall, William H.: Letters, newspaper clipping, 1861, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Atkinson, James S.: Letter, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Auchmuty, Robert: Letter, newspaper clipping, etching, biographical note, 1779, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bache: Letters, 1823-1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bailey, Theodorus: Letter, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters (2 of 7; see also OS), 1805-1814 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters (3 of 7), 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters (4 of 7), 1815-1822 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters (5 of 7), 1823-1824 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters, transcript (6 of 7), 1825-1826 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bainbridge, William: Letters (7 of 7), 1825-1843 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ballard, H.E.: Letter, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bancroft, G.: Letters, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Barnes, John Sanford: Letters about John Paul Jones, 1896-1909 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barnes, John Sanford: Letters, 1863-1910 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Barnes, John Sanford: Letters, 1801-1909 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Barney: Letters, 1864, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Barron, James: Letters, 1837-1882 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Beatty: Letters, 1815, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bell, H.H.: Letters, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Berrien, J.: Letter, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Blagge, J.: Letter, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Blair, M.: Letters, 1861,1869 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Blake: Letters, 1836, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bolton, W.C.: Letters, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Branch: Letters, 1829-1830 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Breese, Samuel: Letters, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bridge, H.: Letters, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Brownson, Willard H.: Letters, clippings, 1907, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bunce, Francis M.: Letters, 1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Burden, J.: Letter, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Burrows: Letter, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bush: Letter, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bushnell, C.: Letters, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Calhoun, John C.: Order, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Campbell, Hugh: Letter, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Case, A. Ludlow: Form letter, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Cathcart, James Leander: Letter, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Chadwick, French E.: Letters, 1900-1907 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Chase, Salmon: Letter, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Chauncey, Isaac: Letters, 1815-1832 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Also includes one letter from Isaac Chauncey's brother, Ichabod Wolcott Chauncey (1821).
  - Conner: Letter, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Conyngham, Gustavus: Passports, ledger sheets, 1808, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Coules, William: Letters, 1884-1902 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Crane: Letter, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Creighton, J.B.: Letter, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Crowninshield, B.W.: Letters, 1815-1818 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Cunningham, R.B.: Letter, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Misc. C: Letters, 1777-1793 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Davis, George: Letter, 1814 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dacres, J.W.: Letter, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dahlgreen, J.A.: Letter, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dale, Richard: Letters, photographs, receipt, will, 1794-1826, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dana, Richard Henry: Letters, 1868-1869 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Decatur: Letters, 1825-1835, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dewey, Admiral George: Letters, clippings, 1892-1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Dobbin: Letter, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Downes: Letter, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Drayton: Letter, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Misc. D: Letters, appropriation form, clipping, 1841-1861, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Eckford, Henry: Contracts, 1807-1809 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Elliott, J.: Letters, 1823-1843 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fairfax, D.M: Letters, 1870, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Farragut, D.: Letters, deed, 1824-1907 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Foote, Andrew: Letters, 1840-1862 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ford, Thomas G.: Typescript autobiography, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fox: Letter, copy of newspaper article, 1866, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Frailey: Letter, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fulton, Robert: Letter, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gambier: Certificate, 1814 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Geisinger: Letter, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Gillon: Letter transcripts, original, 1783-1787, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Goldsborough: Letters, 1810-1843 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Goodrich, Caspar F.: Letters, 1898-1907 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gordon: Letters, 1813-1842 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Gregory, Francis H.: Letters, 1843, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hamilton, Paul: Letters, 1809-1812 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hancock, John: Commission, letter, 1776, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Haraden, J: Bill of exchange, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Harwood, Andrew: Letters, 1839-1861 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hayes, Richard Somers: Letters, clippings, 1832-1905 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Henley: Letter, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Henshaw, David: Letters, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hoff, William Bainbridge: Letters, 1842-1881 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Huger, Benjamin: Letters, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hull, Isaac: Letters, legal documents, photostats, 1799-1846, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Humphreys: Letter transcripts, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Misc. H: Letters, receipt, 1777-1840 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Ingraham, D.: Letters, 1842-1860 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Irwin: Letters, clippings, 1862-1898, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Jefferson, Thomas: Letter, 1781 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Johnson, Richard M.: Letters, clipping, 1828-1835, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Jones: Letters, order, 1813-1865 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Misc. J: Letters, 1882-1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Kane, J. Nicholson: Letter, Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Kennedy, John P.: Letters, 1852-1853 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - King, Rufus: Letter, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Lincoln, Robert T.: Letter, 1865 (Box 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter from Robert Todd Lincoln, on mourning stationery, to Gustavus Vasa Fox, transmitting a lock of Abraham Lincoln's hair. Framed.
  - Livingston, Robert: Letter, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Longstreet: Letters, 1892-1896 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Low, Seth: Letters, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Luce, S.B.: Letters, 1873-1875 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Misc. L: Letters, legal documents, 1756-1892, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Madison, James; Letter, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Maffitt, John Newland: Letter, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mahan, A.: Letters, 1898-1907 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mallory: Letter, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Marston, John: Letters, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Meade: Letters, 1869-1894 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mercer: Letters, 1843-1861 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Missroon: Letters, 1841-1844, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Morris: Letters, 1803-1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Misc. M: Letters, clippings, 1835-1899 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Misc. N: Letters, petitions, 1780-1849 (Box 3, Folder 6)